Curriculum Vitae - Ahmed Qureshi

CONTACT Information Advanced Robotics Lab Phone: +1-858-349-8122
University of California E-mail: a1quresh@eng.ucsd.edu
San Diego, CA 92093-0436, USA URL: qureshiahmed.github.io

Research Statement I aim to develop biologically inspired, general-purpose reasoning, planning, and control algorithms for compliant and safe human-robot interaction in the real, dynamic environments for solving complex assistive tasks.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Collaborative Motion Planning & Control, Reinforcement Learning, Deep Learning, Human-Robot Interaction, Approximate Inference, Cognitive Science.

EDUCATION

University of California San Diego, USA

2017 - 2021

PhD, Intelligent Systems, Robotics and Control (CGPA: 4.00/4.00)

- Dissertation Topic: Learning-based motion planners for high-dimensional problems.
- Advisor: Prof. Michael C. Yip

Osaka University, Osaka, Japan

2015 - 2017

M.S, Artificial Intelligence (CGPA: 3.00/3.00)

- Dissertation Topic: Deep Reinforcement Learning for Human-Robot Interaction in the Real-World.
- Advisors: Prof. Hiroshi Ishiguro

National University of Sciences and Technology (NUST), Pakistan

2010 - 2014

Fall, 2011

B.S., Electrical Engineering (CGPA: 3.59/4.00)

- Dissertation Topic: Enhanced RRT* for motion planning in complex cluttered and time-varying environments.
- Advisors: Prof. Yasar Ayaz and Prof. Osman Hasan

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- Teaching Assistant, Advances in Robot Manipulation, UC San Diego
 Co-Instructor, Robot Reinforcement Learning, UC San Diego
 Teaching Assistant, Cognitive Neuroscience Robotics I & II, Osaka University
 Feb, 2016 2017
- Instructor, Variational Inference (derivation and examples), Osaka University
 Instructor, Deep learning and its applications, Osaka University
 Fall, 2015
- Teaching Assistant, Circuits Analysis, National University of Sciences & Technology

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Intern

Sep, 2020 - Dec, 2020

NVIDIA Robotics Research (Advisor: Dieter Fox), Seattle USA.

Research Student

Apr, 2015 - Aug, 2015

Professor Hiroshi Ishiguro Laboratory, Osaka University, Japan.

Worked as junior researcher on various projects:

- RGB-D based human activity recognition using dual stream convolutional neural network.
- Facial expressions recognition through deep neural networks.
- Collected RGB-D dataset of daily life human activities.

Research Associate

Jul, 2014 - Mar, 2015

Robotics and Intelligence System Engineering (RISE) Lab, NUST, Pakistan.

Worked on various internationally collaborated research projects:

- Solving integrated perception and planning problems for an autonomous wheelchair.
- Team coordinator and co-supervisor of a team qualified for RoboCup Standard-League Challenge (2015).

Research Assistant

Aug, 2012 - Jun, 2014

Robotics and Intelligence System Engineering (RISE) Lab, NUST, Pakistan.

Worked on various AI research problems:

- Path planning in kidney-like environments with narrow passages.
- Path planning in time-varying environments.
- Goal directed sampling heuristics for sampling-based planning methods.
- Person detection and tracking in crowded places.
- Solutions to the perceptual aliasing problem in map generation and localization.
- Optimal collision avoidance method for autonomous vehicles operating in a joint space.

Research Intern

Jan, 2013 - Apr, 2013

Smart Machines and Robotics Technology Lab, NUST, Pakistan.

• Worked on the development of interactive and adaptive welcome system for NUST entrance using Microsoft KINECT sensors and various machine learning techniques.

Research Intern Jul, 2012 - Aug, 2012

Vision Imaging And Signal Processing Lab, NUST, Pakistan.

Worked on the project of robust and efficient pose estimation using Microsoft KINECT Sensor.

PATENTS

P1. M.C.Yip, M.J.Bency, **A.H.Qureshi**. Machine Learning based Fixed-Time Optimal Path Generation, US Patent App. 16/222,706, 2019.

SELECTED
PEER-REVIEWED
JOURNAL

- J8. **A.H.Qureshi**, J.Dong, A.Baig, and M.C.Yip. Constrained Motion Planning Networks X, IEEE Transactions on Robotics 2021. (under review)
- J7. **A.H.Qureshi**, J.Dong, A.Choe, and M.C.Yip. Neural Manipulation Planning on the Constraint Manifolds, IEEE/RAS Robotics and Automation Letters 2020. (IF: 3.608)
- J6. **A.H.Qureshi**, Y.Miao, A.Simeonov, and M.C.Yip. Motion Planning Networks: Bridging the Gap Between Learning-based and Classical Motion Planners, IEEE Transactions on Robotics 2020. (IF: 6.123)
- J5. **A.H.Qureshi**, Y.Nakamura, Y.Yoshikawa and H.Ishiguro. Intrinsically motivated reinforcement learning for human–robot interaction in the real-world, Neural Networks, Vol 107, pp.23-33, 2018. (IF: 7.197)
- J4. Zahid. Tahir, **A.H.Qureshi**, Y.Ayaz and R.Nawaz. Potentially guided bidirectionalized RRT* for fast optimal path planning in cluttered environments, International Journal of Robotics and Autonomous Systems, Elsevier, Vol. 108, pp. 13-27, 2018. (IF: 2.638)
- J3. A.H.Qureshi and Y.Ayaz. Potential Functions Based Sampling Heuristic for Optimal Motion Planning, Autonomous Robots, DOI 10.1007/s10514-015-9518-0, 2015. (IF: 2.066)
- J2. A.H.Qureshi and Y.Ayaz. Intelligent Bidirectional Rapidly-Exploring Random Trees for Op-

timal Motion Planning in Complex Cluttered Environments, International Journal of Robotics and Autonomous Systems, Elsevier, Vol. 68, pp. 1-11, 2015. (IF: 1.256)

J1. A.H.Qureshi, S.Mumtaz, Y.Ayaz, O.Hasan, M.S.Muhammad and M.T.Mahmood.Triangular Geometrised Sampling Heuristic For RRT* Motion Planner, International Journal of Advanced Robotic Systems (IJARS), InTech Publishers, 12:10, 2015, (Top Most Popular Paper of IJARS for 3 consecutive weeks in February - March 2015). (IF: 0.526)

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

- C13. J.Johnson, L.Li, F.Liu, A.H.Qureshi, and M.C.Yip. Dynamically Constrained Motion Planning Networks for Non-Holonomic Robots, Proceedings of IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robot and Systems (IROS), Las Vegas, USA 2021. (to appear)
- C12. A.H.Qureshi, J. J. Johnson, Y. Qin, T. West, B. Boots, and M.C.Yip. Composing Task-Agnostic Policies via Deep Reinforcement Learning, International Conference on Representation Learning (ICLR), 2020.
- C11. **A.H.Qureshi**, B. Boots, and M.C.Yip. Adversarial Imitation Via Variational Inverse Reinforcement Learning, International Conference on Representation Learning (ICLR), 2019.
- C10. A.H.Qureshi, A.Simeonov, M.J.Bency, M.C.Yip. Motion Planning Networks, IEEE/RAS International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), pp. 2118-2124, Montreal, Canada 2019.
- C9. M.J.Bency, A.H.Qureshi, M.C.Yip. Neural Path Planning: Fixed Time, Near-Optimal Path Generation via Oracle Imitation, Proceedings of IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robot and Systems (IROS), pp. 3965-3972, Macau 2019.
- C8. **A.H.Qureshi** and Michael.C.Yip . Deeply Informed Neural Sampling For Robot Motion Planning, Proceedings of IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robot and Systems (IROS), pp. 6582-6588, Madrid, Spain 2018.
- C7. A.H.Qureshi, Z.Tahir, G.Tariq, Y.Ayaz. Re-planning Using Delaunay Triangulation for Real Time Motion Planning in Complex Dynamic Environments, IEEE/ASME International Conference on Advanced Intelligent Mechatronics (AIM), pp. 905-911, Auckland, New Zealand 2018.
- C6. A.H.Qureshi, Y.Nakamura, Y.Yoshikawa and H.Ishiguro. Show, Attend and Interact: Perceivable Social Human-Robot Interaction through Neural Attention Q-Network, Proceedings of IEEE/RAS International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), pp.1639-1645, Singapore 2017.
- C5. **A.H.Qureshi**, Y.Nakamura, Y.Yoshikawa and H.Ishiguro. Robot gains social intelligence through multimodal deep reinforcement learning, Proceedings of IEEE/RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots, pp. 745-751, Cancun Mexico, 2016.
- C4. **A.H.Qureshi**, S.Mumtaz, Y. Ayaz, and O. Hasan. Augmenting RRT*-Planner with Local Trees for Motion Planning in Complex Dynamic Environments, Proceedings of IEEE/RAS 19th International Conference on Methods and Models in Automation and Robotics (MMAR), pp. 657-662, Miedzyzdroje, Poland 2014.
- C3. A.H.Qureshi, S.Mumtaz, Y.Ayaz, O.Hasan and W.Y.Kim. Adaptive Potential guided directional-RRT*, Proceedings of International Conference on Robotics and Biomimetics (ROBIO), pp. 1887-1892, China, 2013.
- C2. B.Ali, A.H.Qureshi, Y.Ayaz, N.Muhammad and W.Y.Kim. Human tracking by a mobile robot

using 3D features, Proceedings of International Conference on Robotics and Biomimetics (ROBIO), pp. 2464-2469, Shenzhen, China, 2013.

C1. A.H.Qureshi, K.F.Iqbal, S.M.Qamar, F.Islam, Y.Ayaz and N.Muhammad. Potential guided directional-RRT* for accelerated motion planning in cluttered environments, Proceedings of International Conference on Mechatronics and Automation (ICMA), pp. 519-524, Takamatsu, Japan, 2013.

Workshop Papers

W3. A.H.Qureshi, Y.Miao M.C.Yip. Active Continual Learning for Planning and Navigation, ICML Workshop on Real World Experiment Design and Active Learning 2020.

W2. **A.H.Qureshi**, M.C.Yip. Adversarial Reward and Policy learning Via Variational Inverse Optimal Control, Bay Area Machine Learning Symposium, August 2018.

W1. **A.H.Qureshi**, Y. Nakamura, Y. Yoshikawa, H. Ishiguro. Robot Learns Responsive Behavior through Interaction with People using Deep Reinforcement Learning, 3rd International Symposium on Cognitive Neuroscience Robotics, Dec 2016.

Honors and Awards

- Two gold medals for outstanding undergraduate research by Pakistan Book of Records, 2019.
- Outstanding Young Researcher by Heidelberg Laureate Forum, 2018.
- Japanese Government MEXT Scholarship, 2015-2017.
- NUST GPA-based scholarship, 2010-2014.

Seminar & Talks

- Emergence of a Mutualistic Relationship between Motion Planning and Machine Learning for Scalable Robot Control,
 Institute for Neural Computation Chalk Talk Series, UC San Diego, Oct 2020.
- Motion Planning Networks, University of Toronto, Canada (Virtual), Sep 2020.
- Deep Learning For Robotics, Neural Computing & Deep Learning Workshop, 6th Heidelberg Laureate Forum, Germany, Sep 2018.
- Learning-based motion planning and control, CRI Seminars, University of California San Diego, May 2018.
- Intrinsically Motivated Reinforcement Learning for Human-Robot Interaction in the Real-World, Artificial Intelligence Seminars, Osaka University, Japan, Nov 2017.
- Living with Robots- The Next Generation of Intelligent Machines, Information Technology University, Pakistan, Mar 2016.
- Sampling-based motion planning algorithms, Topics in Robotics Session, Osaka University, Japan, Apr 2015.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming Languages: C/C++, Python, Lua, Cmake, MATLAB etc.
- Machine Learning Tools: TensorFlow, PyTorch, libTorch, Scikit-learn, OpenCV, PyMC3.
- Robotic Software: ROS, Gazebo, OpenRave, OMPL, V-REP, Mujoco, MoveIt.
- Operating Systems: Linux, Macintosh, Windows.

STUDENT ADVISING & MENTORING

- Anthony Simeonov (PhD student at MIT, USA)
- Mayur Bency (Research Engineer at Oracle Corporation)
- Zaid Tahir (PhD student at Boston University, USA)
- Isabella Constantin (Resident at Microsoft, UK)
- Zhixian Ye (Research Engineer at Baidu, USA)
- Jacob Johnson (PhD student at UC San Diego, USA)
- Yinglong Miao (PhD student at Rutgers University, USA)
- Asfiya Baig (MS student at UC San Diego, USA)
- Ayon Biswas (MS student at UC San Diego, USA)

- Jiangeng Dong (MS student at UC San Diego, USA)
- Linjun Li (Research Engineer at UC San Diego, USA)
- Leon Dai (MS student at UC San Diego, USA)
- Saurabh Mirani (MS student at UC San Diego, USA)
- Austin Choe (MS student at UC San Diego, USA)
- Yahsiu Hsieh (MS student at UC San Diego, USA)
- Yuhze Qin (MS student at UC San Diego, USA)

Professional Activities

Workshop Organization:

• Organizer, Workshop on *Learning Representations for Planning and Control*, IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robot and Systems (IROS), Macau, China, Nov 2019.

Reviewer:

Journals:

- Elsevier Neural Networks;
- IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters;
- Cambridge Robotica;

Conferences:

- IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)
- IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS).

References

Available upon request